to have you with us today. My name is Zvezda and I would like to welcome you in front of the
오늘 여러분과 함께하게 되어 기쁩니다. 제 이름은 즈베즈다이고, 여러분을 환영합니다.
whole Jobrity team. For those who maybe don't know who we are, we are a developers community
조브리티 팀 전체입니다. 우리가 누군지 모르시는 분들을 위해 설명하자면, 우리는 개발자 커뮤니티입니다.
with more than 70,000 users and a place where you can explore IT companies, IT jobs and read
70,000명 이상의 사용자와 함께 IT 기업, IT 직무를 탐색하고 읽을 수 있는 공간입니다.
experiences from your colleagues from the industry. We are currently present in six markets
업계 동료들의 경험을 공유할 수 있습니다. 현재 6개 시장에 진출해 있습니다.
Serbia, Croatia, Romania, Bulgaria, Macedonia and Slovenia and we strongly believe that sharing is
세르비아, 크로아티아, 루마니아, 불가리아, 마케도니아, 슬로베니아에 진출해 있습니다.
caring and that is why we have started this series of free webinars with industry experts.
배려라고 믿기 때문에 업계 전문가들과 함께 무료 웨비나 시리즈를 시작하게 되었습니다.
This is our eighth webinar and today we are going to be talking about modular monoliths.
이번 웨비나는 여덟 번째 웨비나로, 오늘은 모듈형 모놀리스에 대해 이야기할 예정입니다.
We are happy to welcome Milan. Milan, welcome and thank you for being here. Milan is a software
밀라노를 만나게 되어 반갑습니다. 밀란, 와주셔서 감사합니다. 밀라노는 소프트웨어입니다.
architect and tech youtuber and he will be sharing with us some tips and tricks on how to build the
건축가이자 기술 유튜버로, 오늘 이 자리에서 소프트웨어 개발과 관련된 몇 가지 팁과 요령을 공유할 예정입니다.
modular monolith and lessons that he has learned along the way. And one more thing, we're going to
모듈형 모놀리스를 만드는 방법과 그 과정에서 얻은 교훈을 공유합니다. 그리고 한 가지 더, 우리는
be having a Q&A session on the end of the webinar so please feel free to ask any questions that you
웨비나 마지막에 Q&A 세션이 있을 예정이니 궁금한 점이 있으면 언제든지 질문해 주세요.
maybe have for Milan or for us in the Q&A section. I don't want to be wasting our precious time any
Q&A 세션에서 밀라노나 저희에게 궁금한 점이 있으시다면 언제든지 질문해 주세요. 우리의 소중한 시간을 낭비하고 싶지 않습니다.
longer so Milan, the floor is all yours. Thank you for the delightful introduction.
밀라노, 바닥은 모두 당신의 것입니다. 유쾌한 소개 감사합니다.
And thank you to Jyobrati for extending this invitation to me. It's an honor to be talking to
그리고 저에게 초대를 해주신 조브라티에게도 감사드립니다. 함께 이야기할 수 있어서 영광입니다.
you today. My name is Milan. I'm a software architect by day and content creator in my spare time.
영광입니다. 제 이름은 밀란입니다. 낮에는 소프트웨어 아키텍트, 여가 시간에는 콘텐츠 크리에이터로 일하고 있습니다.
Although you could argue that creating content is my primary occupation,
콘텐츠 제작이 제 본업이라고 할 수도 있겠지만요,
given how much I share daily on the various social medias that I'm present on, you can find me on
제가 현재 활동하고 있는 다양한 소셜 미디어에서 매일 얼마나 많은 것을 공유하는지를 고려할 때, 여러분은 저를 찾을 수 있습니다.
YouTube, LinkedIn, Twitter and on my website where I write a weekly blog. You can see all the links
유튜브, 링크드인, 트위터, 그리고 제가 매주 블로그를 작성하는 웹사이트에서 찾을 수 있습니다. 모든 링크를 볼 수 있습니다.
on the screen. And without further ado, I'm going to jump into what you all came here for today,
화면에서 볼 수 있습니다. 더 이상 고민할 필요 없이 여러분들이 오늘 이 자리에 모인 이유에 대해 알아보도록 하겠습니다,
which is modular monoliths. I'm going to talk about my experience using this architecture on
모듈형 모놀리스입니다. 이 아키텍처를 사용한 제 경험에 대해 이야기하겠습니다.
a real project for the past two years. I'm going to explain as best as I can how you can build a
지난 2년간 실제 프로젝트에 사용했습니다. 제가 할 수 있는 한 최선을 다해 설명해드리겠습니다.
modular monolith and what are some of the lessons that we learned along the way. Unfortunately,
모듈형 모놀리스를 구축하는 방법과 그 과정에서 얻은 교훈이 무엇인지 설명하겠습니다. 불행히도,
we had to learn those lessons the hard way, but I'm hoping that in sharing my experience today,
그 교훈을 힘들게 배워야 했지만, 오늘 제 경험을 공유하면서 그 교훈이 도움이 되었으면 좋겠습니다,
you're going to be able to learn those lessons right away and you won't make the same mistakes
여러분은 그 교훈을 바로 배울 수 있고 같은 실수를 하지 않을 것입니다.
that we did. So what is our agenda for today? We're going to briefly talk about the monolith
우리가 했던 것처럼요. 그럼 오늘의 의제는 무엇일까요? 모놀리스에 대해 간단히 이야기해 보겠습니다.
architecture. Then we're going to jump into microservices just on a high level. I'm also going
아키텍처에 대해 간단히 이야기하겠습니다. 그런 다음 마이크로서비스에 대해 개괄적으로 살펴보겠습니다. 또한
to do a comparison between monoliths and microservices. And then we're going to do a deep
모놀리스와 마이크로서비스를 비교해 보겠습니다. 그런 다음 심층적인 분석을 할 것입니다.
dive into modular monoliths. I'm going to explain what this architecture is, how you can build one,
모듈형 모놀리스에 대해 알아보겠습니다. 이 아키텍처가 무엇인지, 어떻게 구축할 수 있는지 설명하겠습니다,
what are the challenges of actually building a proper modular monolith, and what are some of the
실제로 제대로 된 모듈형 모놀리스를 구축하는 데 있어 어떤 어려움이 있는지, 그리고 어떤 점이
lessons that I learned along the way. So here you can see the monolith. What we mean when we say
교훈을 얻었습니다. 여기 모놀리스가 보입니다. 우리가 말하는 의미는
monolith architecture is we have just one application representing the system. Typically,
모놀리스 아키텍처는 시스템을 대표하는 애플리케이션이 하나뿐이라는 뜻입니다. 일반적으로,
it's going to be one solution if you are working in a .NET environment, so that one solution with
이면 하나의 솔루션이 되지만, .NET 환경에서 작업하는 경우라면
one executable represents the monolith. And these days, it's considered kind of old-fashioned.
하나의 실행 파일이 모놀리스를 나타냅니다. 그리고 요즘에는 다소 구식으로 간주됩니다.
Everybody wants to be working in some other kind of architecture because it looks cool on
모두가 다른 종류의 아키텍처에서 일하고 싶어하는 이유는 그것이 멋져 보이기 때문입니다.
CVs, among other things, but I think there is a lot of beauty in creating a good solid monolith,
이력서 등 여러 가지가 있겠지만, 좋은 견고한 모놀리스를 만드는 데는 많은 아름다움이 있다고 생각합니다,
which is why I'm trying to talk about modular monoliths, which are, in my opinion,
그래서 저는 모듈형 모놀리스에 대해 이야기하려고 합니다,
a good way to build monoliths. And one of the issues with monoliths and why people
모놀리스를 구축하는 좋은 방법이라고 생각합니다. 그리고 모놀리스의 문제점 중 하나와 사람들이 왜
moved away from them is limited scalability. And what I mean by this is you only have one
모놀리스로부터 멀어지는 이유 중 하나는 확장성이 제한된다는 것입니다. 즉, 모놀리스에는 단 하나의
application, one system, and if you want to scale something, you only can scale that system. I'm
애플리케이션, 하나의 시스템만 있고, 무언가를 확장하려면 해당 시스템만 확장할 수 있다는 뜻입니다. 나는
going to talk about this more in just a moment. On the other end of the spectrum, we have
잠시 후에 이에 대해 더 자세히 설명하겠습니다. 스펙트럼의 다른 쪽 끝에는 다음이 있습니다.
microservices. So here's our representation of a very complicated system where each node on the
마이크로서비스가 있습니다. 따라서 여기에서는 각 노드가
screen is one microservice. And I'm sure there are actually real-world systems that look a lot
화면의 각 노드가 하나의 마이크로서비스입니다. 실제 시스템도 이와 비슷할 것입니다.
like this. And if you're working in a system like this, I am sure you're having a lot of fun.
이렇게 생겼을 겁니다. 이런 시스템에서 일하고 계신다면 정말 재미있게 일하고 계실 겁니다.
So when we say microservices, we mean that many individual services, each doing their own job,
마이크로 서비스란 각각 고유한 업무를 수행하는 수많은 개별 서비스를 의미합니다,
form the whole larger system. These days, it's considered cutting edge and cool. Everybody wants
더 큰 전체 시스템을 구성합니다. 요즘에는 이런 방식이 최첨단이고 멋지다고 여겨집니다. 모두가 원하는
to be working with microservices because they are very popular, mainly because it's challenging to
마이크로서비스가 매우 인기가 있기 때문에 마이크로서비스 작업을 하려고 합니다.
work with them, but it's also fun and exciting. And one strong advantage of microservices
하지만 재미있고 흥미롭기도 합니다. 그리고 마이크로서비스의 강력한 장점 중 하나는
is that at least in theory, they are infinitely scalable because whenever you want to scale
적어도 이론상으로는 무한히 확장할 수 있다는 것입니다.
something, you can scale that service either vertically or horizontally, or if you have
무언가를 확장하고 싶을 때마다 해당 서비스를 수직 또는 수평으로 확장 할 수 있습니다.
a bottleneck, you can extract it into a separate service and then scale that independently.
병목 현상이 발생하면 이를 별도의 서비스로 추출한 다음 독립적으로 확장할 수 있습니다.
So let's try to compare monoliths and microservices on a few points.
이제 몇 가지 점에서 모놀리스와 마이크로서비스를 비교해 보겠습니다.
The first is in terms of deployment. For monoliths, we have one deployment artifact,
첫 번째는 배포 측면입니다. 모놀리스의 경우 배포 아티팩트가 하나 있습니다,
whereas for microservices, we have many, or rather for each service that is part of our
반면, 마이크로서비스의 경우, 우리는 많은, 아니 오히려 우리의 일부인 각 서비스에 대해
microservice system, we have a deployment artifact. And for microservices, you're going to find that
마이크로서비스 시스템에는 배포 아티팩트가 있습니다. 그리고 마이크로서비스의 경우, 다음과 같은 것을 발견하게 될 것입니다.
deployment is generally a lot more complicated and a lot more things can go wrong than with monoliths.
배포는 일반적으로 모놀리스보다 훨씬 더 복잡하고 더 많은 일이 잘못될 수 있습니다.
When it comes to communication, in a monolith, typically components talk to each other
통신과 관련하여, 모놀리스에서는 일반적으로 컴포넌트가 서로 통신합니다.
by simple method calls, given the nature of the system is everything is in one physical
간단한 메서드 호출로 모든 것이 하나의 물리적인 객체에 있다는 시스템의 특성을 고려할 때
application. And with microservices, it's a little bit different because each of your service is an
애플리케이션에 있습니다. 그리고 마이크로서비스의 경우, 각 서비스가 개별적인
independent application running in its own server. So your services, if they want to talk to each
자체 서버에서 실행되는 독립적인 애플리케이션입니다. 따라서 서비스가 각각의 서버와 통신하려면
other, they have to resort to using network calls, typically using HTTP, but there are other approaches
다른 경우에는 네트워크 호출을 사용해야 합니다. 일반적으로 HTTP를 사용하지만 다른 접근 방식도 있습니다.
like messaging, for example. Now, when it comes to scalability, monoliths are usually
메시징과 같은 다른 접근 방식도 있습니다. 이제 확장성과 관련하여 모놀리스는 일반적으로 다음과 같습니다.
vertically scalable very easily. You can always beef up that server where your monolith is running,
수직적으로 매우 쉽게 확장할 수 있습니다. 모놀리스가 실행 중인 서버를 언제든지 강화할 수 있습니다,
make it a bigger machine, and you can horizontally scale a monolith, but the downside is you're
더 큰 머신으로 만들 수 있고, 모놀리스를 수평으로 확장할 수 있지만, 단점이 있습니다.
scaling the entire application and not necessarily the bottleneck that is probably causing you
전체 애플리케이션을 확장할 때 병목현상이 발생할 수 있다는 것입니다.
trouble. Where with microservices, you have the freedom to scale both horizontally and vertically
문제. 마이크로서비스에서는 수평적, 수직적 확장이 자유롭습니다.
and even extract services from your existing services if you need to scale some part of your
확장해야 하는 경우 기존 서비스에서 서비스를 추출할 수도 있습니다.
system further. When it comes to databases, in a monolith system, you will typically only have
시스템을 더 확장할 수도 있습니다. 데이터베이스의 경우, 모놀리스 시스템에서는 일반적으로 다음과 같은 것만 있습니다.
one database, which is very easy to work with. And with microservices, you have usually one
하나의 데이터베이스만 있어 작업하기가 매우 쉽습니다. 그리고 마이크로서비스의 경우 일반적으로 하나의
database per service, but your entire system is comprised of many individual databases,
데이터베이스가 있지만, 전체 시스템은 여러 개의 개별 데이터베이스로 구성되어 있습니다,
which adds another layer of complexity.
또 다른 복잡성 계층이 추가됩니다.
Transactions are available almost out of the box with monoliths because you are usually working
모놀리스를 사용하면 트랜잭션을 거의 즉시 사용할 수 있습니다.
with just one database, so you are transactional by the nature of the system. And with microservices,
단 하나의 데이터베이스로 작업하기 때문에 시스템 특성상 트랜잭션이 가능합니다. 그리고 마이크로서비스도 마찬가지입니다,
it becomes very interesting because if you want to enforce consistency among services,
서비스 간에 일관성을 적용하려는 경우 매우 흥미로워집니다,
you have to resort to using distributed transactions, which they slow performance
분산 트랜잭션을 사용해야 하므로 성능이 느려집니다.
and they introduce a lot of complexity the more services you're trying to keep consistent,
그리고 일관성을 유지하려는 서비스가 많아질수록 복잡성이 커집니다,
which is why people typically tend to trade off consistency and embrace eventual consistency.
그렇기 때문에 사람들은 일반적으로 일관성을 희생하고 궁극적인 일관성을 수용하는 경향이 있습니다.
Where you commit a transaction inside of a single service, which is transactional or consistent,
단일 서비스 내에서 트랜잭션을 커밋하는 경우, 트랜잭션 또는 일관성,
and then you somehow notify the other services in your system of the change that happened,
그리고 나서 어떻게든 시스템의 다른 서비스에 변경 사항을 알립니다,
and eventually your system converges to a consistent state.
결국 시스템이 일관된 상태로 수렴합니다.
And when it comes to scaling teams, again, we have kind of opposing
그리고 팀 확장에 관해서는, 다시 한 번 말씀드리지만, 우리는 일종의 반대 의견을 가지고 있습니다.
points. With a monolith, it becomes difficult to scale with a large team because everybody
포인트가 있습니다. 모놀리스를 사용하면 모든 사람이 한 팀에 속해 있기 때문에 대규모 팀으로 확장하기가 어렵습니다.
is working in the same code base. There are a lot of conflicts, a lot of teams making changes to
동일한 코드 베이스에서 작업하기 때문입니다. 많은 충돌이 발생하고, 많은 팀에서
potentially the same parts of code, and it's kind of messy to work with. With microservices,
코드의 동일한 부분을 변경하는 경우가 많아서 작업하기가 다소 지저분합니다. 마이크로서비스에서는 더욱 그렇습니다,
you can make sure the service is large enough to fill the needs of your team and not small enough
서비스가 팀의 요구 사항을 충족할 수 있을 만큼 충분히 큰지, 너무 작지는 않은지 확인할 수 있습니다.
so that nobody has enough work to do. So it's very easy to scale microservices with large teams,
아무도 할 일이 부족하지 않도록 할 수 있습니다. 따라서 대규모 팀으로 마이크로서비스를 확장하기가 매우 쉽습니다,
where each team can be responsible for one or more services, depending on how big your services are.
서비스 규모에 따라 각 팀이 하나 이상의 서비스를 담당할 수 있습니다.
So I have a quote here from a guy named Martin Fowler. You might have heard of him.
마틴 파울러라는 사람의 말을 인용하겠습니다. 들어보셨을 겁니다.
He's actually very influential in our industry, and he said,
그는 실제로 우리 업계에서 매우 영향력 있는 사람입니다,
you shouldn't start a new project with microservices, even if you're sure your
마이크로서비스로 새 프로젝트를 시작해서는 안 된다고 말합니다.
application will be big enough to make it worthwhile. Now I'm going to give you a moment
애플리케이션이 충분히 가치가 있다고 확신하더라도 말입니다. 이제 잠시 시간을 내어
to ponder on this quote and try to think of what he actually tried to tell us when he said this.
이 인용문을 곰곰이 생각해보고 그가 실제로 이 말을 했을 때 우리에게 무엇을 말하려고 했는지 생각해보세요.
So in my eyes, the reason you shouldn't be starting a project with microservices
제 생각에 마이크로서비스로 프로젝트를 시작해서는 안 되는 이유는 다음과 같습니다.
is because you are going to have a tendency to create, to make your system very granular.
시스템을 매우 세분화해서 만들려는 경향이 있기 때문입니다.
You're going to want to make microservice for this and microservice for that. And before you know it,
이것도 마이크로서비스, 저것도 마이크로서비스를 만들고 싶을 것입니다. 그러다 보면 어느새
you have dozens of microservices. Whereas if you started with a monolith application
수십 개의 마이크로서비스를 갖게 됩니다. 반면에 모놀리스 애플리케이션으로 시작했다면
and then worked with that for as long as you could have, and the benefit of that is you're
로 시작한 다음 가능한 한 오래 작업할 수 있으며, 그 이점은 다음과 같습니다.
going to naturally see where the bottlenecks are in your system. And when bottlenecks start to
시스템의 병목 지점을 자연스럽게 파악할 수 있다는 것입니다. 그리고 병목 현상이 시작되면
appearing in your system, that's a very good sign that that part of your system can be scaled out
이 나타나기 시작하면 시스템의 해당 부분을 확장할 수 있다는 매우 좋은 신호입니다.
into a separate service. So it's kind of a more natural evolution towards microservices.
별도의 서비스로 확장할 수 있다는 뜻입니다. 따라서 마이크로서비스로의 자연스러운 진화라고 할 수 있습니다.
But again, if you build a monolith the traditional way,
하지만 전통적인 방식으로 모놀리스를 구축한다면,
moving into microservices becomes a little bit difficult. So what if we could have the best
마이크로서비스로 이동하는 것이 조금 어려워집니다. 그래서 만약 우리가 최고의
of both worlds? If we could get the physical architecture of a monolith,
두 세계의 장점을 모두 누릴 수 있다면 어떨까요? 모놀리스의 물리적 아키텍처를 얻을 수 있다면요,
where everything is still inside of one system and one physical application, one deployment
모든 것이 여전히 하나의 시스템과 하나의 물리적 애플리케이션, 하나의 배포 안에 있습니다.
artifact. And on the other hand, we have a logical architecture of microservices,
아티팩트. 반면에 우리는 마이크로서비스의 논리적 아키텍처를 가지고 있습니다,
where individual features of the system are kind of naturally grouped together in a way that
시스템의 개별 기능이 다음과 같은 방식으로 자연스럽게 그룹화됩니다.
are kind of naturally grouped together as they would be inside of a microservice.
마이크로서비스 내부에 있는 것처럼 자연스럽게 함께 그룹화됩니다.
And another benefit is to have the ability to move to a microservice architecture easily.
또 다른 이점은 마이크로서비스 아키텍처로 쉽게 이동할 수 있다는 것입니다.
So we can achieve this and it is called a modular monolith. So I'm going to try to explain now
그래서 우리는 이를 달성할 수 있으며 이를 모듈형 모놀리스라고 부릅니다. 이제 설명해 보겠습니다.
what a modular monolith is. And I'm going to start by sharing a few definitions
모듈형 모놀리스가 무엇인지 설명하겠습니다. 먼저 몇 가지 정의를 공유하면서 시작하겠습니다.
of the modular monolith with you. So the first definition says a modular monolith is a software
모듈형 모놀리스에 대한 몇 가지 정의를 공유하겠습니다. 첫 번째 정의에 따르면 모듈형 모놀리스는 소프트웨어가 아닌
design approach in which a monolith is designed with an emphasis on interchangeable and potentially
모놀리스가 상호 교환 가능하고 잠재적으로 확장 가능한 것에 중점을 두고 설계되는 디자인 접근 방식입니다.
reusable modules. So this is kind of a long definition, but the highlight is interchangeable
재사용 가능한 모듈을 강조하는 설계 방식입니다. 정의가 다소 길지만, 핵심은 상호 교환이 가능하다는 것입니다.
and reusable modules. Okay, let's see another definition. So a modular monolith is an explicit
재사용 가능한 모듈입니다. 자, 다른 정의를 살펴보겠습니다. 모듈형 모놀리스는 명시적으로
name for a monolith system designed in a modular way. So we can see that kind of everything revolves
모듈 방식으로 설계된 모놀리스 시스템의 이름입니다. 그래서 우리는 그런 종류의 모든 것이 회전하는 것을 볼 수 있습니다.
around the word modular. And the definition of the word modular is consisting of separate parts
모듈러라는 단어를 중심으로 돌아간다는 것을 알 수 있습니다. 그리고 모듈러라는 단어의 정의는 별도의 부품으로 구성되어 있습니다.
that when combined form a complete whole. I'm not going to read the rest of the definition,
결합되었을 때 완전한 전체를 형성합니다. 나머지 정의는 읽지 않겠습니다,
but the main point here is you have distinct parts in your system that are kind of independent
하지만 여기서 중요한 점은 시스템에는 독립적인 부분이 있다는 것입니다.
on their own, but together when they comprise, when they come together, they form a complete
그 자체로는 독립적이지만, 함께 구성될 때, 함께 모이면 완전한
system. In our world, this is going to be an application. So everything is easier to visualize
시스템이 됩니다. 우리 세계에서는 이것이 애플리케이션이 될 것입니다. 따라서 모든 것이 더 쉽게 시각화됩니다.
with a diagram. So I prepared a monolith diagram here of a sample eShop application or e-commerce
다이어그램으로 시각화할 수 있습니다. 그래서 저는 여기에 샘플 eShop 애플리케이션 또는 전자 상거래의 모놀리스 다이어그램을 준비했습니다.
application, if you will. And I did actually work on a similar system for the previous two years.
애플리케이션의 모놀리스 다이어그램을 준비했습니다. 저는 실제로 지난 2년 동안 비슷한 시스템에서 일한 적이 있습니다.
So I'm using that as an inspiration. So if it were a monolith, a typical monolith
그래서 저는 그것을 영감으로 삼고 있습니다. 그래서 만약 그것이 모놀리스라면, 전형적인 모놀리스라면
architecture, you would have one application. For example, it can be on ASP.NET Core Web API.
아키텍처라면 하나의 애플리케이션이 있을 것입니다. 예를 들어, ASP.NET 코어 웹 API에 있을 수 있습니다.
And all of the components in our system are going to be C-Sharp class libraries, for example.
그리고 우리 시스템의 모든 컴포넌트는 예를 들어 C-Sharp 클래스 라이브러리가 될 것입니다.
And we have just one database in the system. Now, if we were to convert this system into
그리고 시스템에는 단 하나의 데이터베이스가 있습니다. 이제 이 시스템을 다음과 같이 변환한다면
microservices, we could end up with something like this. So here you can see four separate
마이크로서비스로 변환하면 다음과 같은 결과가 나올 수 있습니다. 따라서 여기에는 4개의 개별
microservices. We have the catalog service, which is responsible for telling us what products are
마이크로서비스가 있습니다. 어떤 제품이 있는지 알려주는 카탈로그 서비스가 있습니다.
available in our system to be bought. Then we have the order service, which is responsible for
구매할 수 있는 제품을 알려주는 역할을 합니다. 그런 다음 주문 서비스가 있는데, 이 서비스는 다음을 담당합니다.
creating, managing orders, shipping them, taking care of payments and so on. We have the customer
주문 생성, 관리, 배송, 결제 처리 등을 담당합니다. 고객이 있습니다.
service, which takes care of the users in the system, which are rather the customers.
시스템 내 사용자를 관리하는 서비스, 즉 고객입니다.
And then the collaboration service, which exists so that customers can interact with
그리고 고객과 상호작용할 수 있도록 존재하는 협업 서비스입니다.
sales representatives to create an order because in this system, creating an order
영업 담당자가 주문을 생성할 수 있도록 존재하는 협업 서비스입니다.
is very complicated. It's kind of a custom made e-commerce application.
매우 복잡합니다. 일종의 맞춤형 전자 상거래 애플리케이션입니다.
So you can see kind of the contrast with these two systems. On the one hand, everything is monolithic
이 두 시스템이 어떻게 대조되는지 알 수 있습니다. 한편으로는 모든 것이 모놀리식입니다.
together. On the other hand, everything is kind of nicely organized into individual services,
함께. 반면에 모든 것이 개별 서비스로 잘 정리되어 있습니다,
where each of them provides its own functionalities. So if we were to try to combine
각각 고유한 기능을 제공합니다. 따라서 만약 우리가
these two diagrams into one, where we want to achieve the physical architecture of a monolith,
이 두 다이어그램을 하나로 합쳐서 모놀리스의 물리적 아키텍처를 구현하고자 합니다,
so that we have one system, and yet we want to keep this logical separation that we have
그래서 우리는 하나의 시스템을 가지면서도 우리가 가지고 있는 이 논리적 분리를 유지하고 싶습니다.
with microservices, we would end up with something like this. So this is how a modular monolith would
마이크로서비스를 사용하면 이렇게 될 것입니다. 따라서 모듈형 모놀리스는 이렇게 됩니다.
look like. Each of your services would now become a module inside of your modular monolith.
처럼 보입니다. 이제 각 서비스는 모듈형 모놀리스 내부의 모듈이 됩니다.
But at the end of the day, this is still just one monolithic application. It's one physical
하지만 결국 이것은 여전히 하나의 모놀리식 애플리케이션일 뿐입니다. 하나의 물리적
application. And all of your components or modules inside of the system are interacting with the
애플리케이션입니다. 그리고 시스템 내부의 모든 컴포넌트 또는 모듈은
same database. Now I want to highlight here that there are explicit boundaries around the modules
동일한 데이터베이스와 상호작용합니다. 이제 여기서 강조하고 싶은 것은 모듈 주변에 명시적인 경계가 있다는 것입니다.
and the arrows here are actually all pointing to the database. They don't represent interaction
그리고 여기 화살표는 실제로 모두 데이터베이스를 가리키고 있습니다. 화살표는 상호 작용을 나타내지 않습니다.
between modules, although I will talk about that in a moment. So
상호작용을 나타내지는 않지만, 이에 대해서는 잠시 후에 설명하겠습니다. 그래서
let's talk about what are the challenges of building a modular monolith. And as I walk
모듈형 모놀리스를 구축할 때 어떤 어려움이 있는지 이야기해 보겠습니다. 그리고 제가 걸으면서
you through the challenges, it's going to become a lot clearer how you actually
도전 과제를 해결해 나가다 보면, 실제로 어떻게 모듈형 모놀리스를
should build a modular monolith. So the first challenge is actually identifying and defining
모듈형 모놀리스를 구축해야 하는지 알게 될 것입니다. 따라서 첫 번째 과제는 실제로 모듈형 모놀리스를
your modules and bounded contexts. The second challenge is solving communication between modules.
모듈과 경계 컨텍스트를 식별하고 정의하는 것입니다. 두 번째 과제는 모듈 간의 통신을 해결하는 것입니다.
You'll see that there are multiple approaches to solve this. And the third challenge is solving
이를 해결하기 위한 여러 가지 접근 방식이 있다는 것을 알 수 있습니다. 세 번째 과제는
data independence and isolation. I'll talk about this in depth in the last part.
데이터 독립성과 격리입니다. 이에 대해서는 마지막 부분에서 자세히 설명하겠습니다.
So let's start with defining modules and bounded contexts. So what modules actually are supposed
그럼 모듈과 바운디드 컨텍스트를 정의하는 것부터 시작하겠습니다. 모듈이란 실제로 어떤 것일까요?
to represent are cohesive sets of functionalities, where cohesive means something that naturally fits
표현해야 하는 것은 응집력 있는 기능 집합이며, 여기서 응집력 있는 기능 집합이란
together. So if you recall from our previous example, we had a couple modules. For example,
함께. 이전 예제에서 두 개의 모듈이 있었다는 것을 기억하실 것입니다. 예를 들어
probably something that you can easily relate to is orders. So everything around the orders
아마도 여러분이 쉽게 공감할 수 있는 것은 주문일 것입니다. 따라서 주문과 관련된 모든 것
functionality will naturally flow together into a cohesive set of functionalities. We also call this
의 모든 기능은 자연스럽게 하나의 응집력 있는 기능 집합으로 흘러갑니다. 우리는 이것을
a module. On the other hand, we have a catalog module, which covers everything related to
모듈이라고도 합니다. 반면에 다음과 관련된 모든 것을 다루는 카탈로그 모듈이 있습니다.
representing line items and other things that are available inside of the eShop application. So one
이 모듈은 eShop 애플리케이션 내에서 사용할 수 있는 품목 및 기타 항목을 나타냅니다. 그래서 하나
definition of what the module can be is the term bounded context, which comes from the book
모듈이 무엇일 수 있는지에 대한 정의는 책에서 나온 용어인 바운드 컨텍스트입니다.
Domain Driven Design, which was written by Eric Evans. I recommend everyone should read this book,
에릭 에반스가 쓴 도메인 중심 디자인(Domain Driven Design)에서 나온 용어입니다. 모든 사람이 이 책을 읽어보길 권합니다,
even though even if you may not like the ideas represented in the book and you don't want to use
비록 이 책에 나오는 아이디어가 마음에 들지 않거나
them in your code, that's perfectly fine. But I think you're going to be a better engineer after
코드에 사용하고 싶지 않더라도 괜찮습니다. 하지만 이 책을 읽고 나면 더 나은 엔지니어가 될 수 있을 겁니다.
reading this book because some ideas presented in the book are very, very good. One of those ideas
이 책에 제시된 몇 가지 아이디어가 매우 훌륭하기 때문입니다. 그 아이디어 중 하나
is a bounded context. And what a bounded context means is it represents a boundary within a domain
바운드 컨텍스트입니다. 바운디드 컨텍스트가 의미하는 바는 도메인 내의 경계를 나타냅니다.
where a particular domain model applies. So again, I'm coming back to the definition of modules,
특정 도메인 모델이 적용되는 도메인 내의 경계를 나타냅니다. 다시 모듈의 정의로 돌아와서 설명하겠습니다,
where I highlighted that they kind of represent a boundary around a set of functionalities,
여기서 저는 모듈이 일련의 기능을 둘러싼 경계를 나타낸다고 강조했습니다,
which also aligns with bounded contexts. And an interesting thing with bounded contexts is that
이는 경계 컨텍스트와도 일치합니다. 바운디드 컨텍스트에서 흥미로운 점은
a single entity, or you can envision it as a table in the database, can belong to more than one
단일 엔티티 또는 데이터베이스의 테이블로 상상할 수 있는 엔티티가 둘 이상에 속할 수 있다는 것입니다.
bounded context. An example of that can be a user. A user represents different things in the bounded
바운드 컨텍스트에 속할 수 있습니다. 그 예로 사용자를 들 수 있습니다. 사용자는 바운드 컨텍스트에서 서로 다른 것을 나타냅니다.
context of an order and different thing in the bounded context of a payment and different thing
주문과 다른 사물의 컨텍스트에서 결제와 다른 사물의 컨텍스트에서 다른 사물을 나타냅니다.
in the bounded context of a shipment, for example, but it's still the same physical entity.
예를 들어, 배송의 경계 컨텍스트에서 다른 물건이지만 여전히 동일한 물리적 엔티티입니다.
So one way also to envision modules is that each module can be treated as a separate application.
따라서 모듈을 구상하는 한 가지 방법은 각 모듈을 별도의 애플리케이션으로 취급할 수 있다는 것입니다.
This also has implications in how you define a module in your actual code, which I'm going to
이는 실제 코드에서 모듈을 정의하는 방법에도 영향을 미칩니다.
talk about now. And I want to discuss how do you actually architect an individual module once you
에 대해 이야기하겠습니다. 그리고 개별 모듈을 실제로 어떻게 설계하는지에 대해 논의하고 싶습니다.
have figured out what are these features that you believe belong to this module? What do you do next?
이 모듈에 속한다고 생각되는 기능이 무엇인지 알아냈나요? 그 다음에는 무엇을 할까요?
So I said that you can envision a module as a separate application, which means that you need
모듈을 별도의 애플리케이션으로 상상할 수 있다고 말씀드렸는데, 이는 다음이 필요하다는 뜻입니다.
to apply some sort of architecture to your module. And you're going to have many modules potentially
이 필요하다는 뜻입니다. 그리고 잠재적으로 많은 모듈을 갖게 될 것입니다.
inside of your modular monolith. One example architecture that you can apply is the layered
모듈 모놀리스 안에 잠재적으로 많은 모듈이 있을 것입니다. 적용할 수 있는 아키텍처의 한 가지 예는 계층화된
architecture, which is very standard. You have just three layers, one for your user interface,
아키텍처가 매우 표준적입니다. 사용자 인터페이스를 위한 레이어는 세 개뿐입니다,
which in our case is probably going to be an API. Then you have one layer for your business logic
이 경우 아마도 API가 될 것입니다. 그리고 비즈니스 로직을 위한 하나의 레이어가 있습니다.
and one more layer for the database. Another option for how you can architect a module is using
그리고 데이터베이스용 레이어가 하나 더 있습니다. 모듈을 설계하는 방법에 대한 또 다른 옵션은
the clean architecture. If you're following me on social media, you probably know that I'm a big fan
를 사용하는 것입니다. 소셜 미디어에서 저를 팔로우하고 계신다면 제가 열렬한 팬이라는 것을 알고 계실 겁니다.
of the clean architecture. This is because I've used it extensively on many projects and I have
팬이라는 것을 알고 계실 겁니다. 여러 프로젝트에서 광범위하게 사용해왔고, 그 결과 저는
found it to be very good for solving many problems. With the clean architecture, you can represent
많은 문제를 해결하는 데 매우 유용하다는 것을 알게 되었습니다. 깔끔한 아키텍처로 다음을 표현할 수 있습니다.
your layers of your domain. And when comprised together, all of the layers represent one module
도메인의 레이어를 표현할 수 있습니다. 그리고 모든 레이어를 함께 구성하면 하나의 모듈을 나타냅니다.
and you can have more than one individual modules. And lastly, one architecture that has been gaining
하나 이상의 개별 모듈을 가질 수 있습니다. 마지막으로, 최근 각광받고 있는 아키텍처 중 하나는
a lot of popularity recently is the vertical slice architecture, where you have a vertical slice
최근 많은 인기를 얻고 있는 아키텍처는 수직 슬라이스 아키텍처입니다.
spanning all of the, for example, here are layers of the layered architecture, but kind of all of
를 모두 아우르는, 예를 들어 여기에는 레이어드 아키텍처의 레이어가 있습니다.
them are physically placed together so that it's easier to navigate individual features.
물리적으로 함께 배치되어 개별 기능을 더 쉽게 탐색할 수 있습니다.
So it doesn't matter really which architecture you choose for your modules. You even have the
따라서 모듈에 어떤 아키텍처를 선택하든 상관없습니다. 심지어
freedom to choose different architectures for different modules. But what I want you to take
모듈마다 다른 아키텍처를 선택할 수 있는 자유도 있습니다. 하지만 제가 원하는 것은
out of this is that one module should be architected like an individual application,
하나의 모듈을 개별 애플리케이션처럼 아키텍처를 설계해야 한다는 것입니다,
even though it's part of your monolith. If you want to see a good example of what a
모놀리스의 일부이긴 하지만요. 모놀리스의 좋은 예가 무엇인지 알고 싶다면
modular monolith looks like, here's a link to a repository on GitHub, which contains an example of
모듈형 모놀리스가 어떻게 생겼는지 보고 싶으시다면, GitHub의 리포지토리로 연결되는 링크를 참조하세요.
a modular monolith with domain-driven design. I personally used this repository during my research
도메인 중심 설계의 모듈형 모놀리스입니다. 저는 개인적으로 이 리포지토리를 연구하는 동안 이 리포지토리를 사용했습니다.
of modular monoliths and I found it very, very nice to kind of see what the concept is
모듈형 모놀리스의 개념이 무엇인지 알 수 있어서 매우 좋았습니다.
and then try to kind of expand it with my own ideas.
그리고 제 아이디어로 확장하려고 노력했습니다.
Thank you very much for sharing the link in the chat.
채팅에서 링크를 공유해 주셔서 감사합니다.
So moving on, let's talk about communication between modules.
이제 모듈 간의 통신에 대해 이야기해 보겠습니다.
So every module is going to expose some sort of public API that other modules can call.
모든 모듈은 다른 모듈이 호출할 수 있는 일종의 공용 API를 노출하게 됩니다.
This public API can be maybe an interface that other modules can call to interact with that
이 공용 API는 다른 모듈이 호출하여 상호 작용할 수 있는 인터페이스가 될 수 있습니다.
module that is exposing the public API, or it can be something else. I'm going to talk about that in
모듈이 공개 API를 노출하는 인터페이스일 수도 있고, 다른 것일 수도 있습니다. 이에 대해서는
just a moment. Now, it's important that there are no references allowed to other modules in the
잠시만요. 이제 다른 모듈에 대한 참조가 허용되지 않는 것이 중요합니다.
system except the public API. So if we have two modules, let's for example say that they are
시스템에서 공용 API를 제외한 다른 모듈에 대한 참조가 허용되지 않는다는 것입니다. 예를 들어 두 개의 모듈이 있다고 가정해 보겠습니다.
architected using the vertical slice architecture, they are only allowed to call the public APIs that
수직 슬라이스 아키텍처를 사용하여 설계된 두 모듈이 있다고 가정할 때, 이 모듈은 다음 두 모듈에 해당하는
they expose, and they cannot reference anything else inside of other modules. Now, this, how you
만 호출할 수 있으며, 다른 모듈 내부의 다른 어떤 것도 참조할 수 없습니다. 이제, 어떻게
achieve this is you hide implementation details of your module modules internally. In C-Sharp,
이를 달성하는 방법은 내부적으로 모듈 모듈의 구현 세부 사항을 숨기는 것입니다. C-Sharp에서,
you can achieve this using the internal keyword, which helps you hide the given class that is
내부 키워드를 사용하여 이를 달성할 수 있는데, 이는 주어진 클래스를 숨기는 데 도움이 됩니다.
decorated with this keyword inside of that project. So this is how you can achieve kind
이 키워드로 장식된 클래스를 프로젝트 내부에서 숨길 수 있습니다. 이렇게 하면 다음과 같이
of implementation hiding between modules and only expose a public API that other modules can call.
의 구현을 모듈 사이에 숨기고 다른 모듈이 호출할 수 있는 공용 API만 노출합니다.
Now, when it comes to actually implementing this, you have two approaches. One approach is using
이제 이를 실제로 구현할 때는 두 가지 접근 방식이 있습니다. 한 가지 접근 방식은
metacalls. So let's say the catalog module is exposing a public API and the other module is
메타콜을 사용하는 것입니다. 카탈로그 모듈이 퍼블릭 API를 노출하고 있고 다른 모듈이
interested in calling that API. This is going to be an interface for the catalog module and also
를 호출하는 데 관심이 있다고 가정해 보겠습니다. 이것은 카탈로그 모듈의 인터페이스가 될 것이며, 또한
the implementation is going to reside there, but the order module will be allowed to reference this
구현은 거기에 상주하지만 주문 모듈은 이것을 참조할 수 있습니다.
interface and at runtime it's going to be provided the actual implementation. So the benefit of this
인터페이스를 참조할 수 있게 되고 런타임에 실제 구현이 제공될 것입니다. 따라서 이것의 이점은
approach is it's really fast because you're relying on in-memory calls which are both reliable
접근 방식의 장점은 신뢰할 수 있는 인메모리 호출에 의존하기 때문에 매우 빠르다는 것입니다.
and performant. You can only call the public API of other modules and the problem is,
성능도 뛰어납니다. 다른 모듈의 공용 API만 호출할 수 있다는 점이 문제입니다,
and potential pain point, that this introduces runtime coupling. So you are calling the public
런타임 커플링이 발생한다는 점과 잠재적인 문제점이 있습니다. 따라서 공용
interface of another module, but at runtime an interface can be instantiated. So if you are using
인터페이스를 호출할 수 있지만 런타임에 인터페이스가 인스턴스화될 수 있습니다. 따라서 만약 당신이
the interface, something has to implement that interface and actually run that code. So you're
을 사용한다면, 무언가가 해당 인터페이스를 구현하고 실제로 해당 코드를 실행해야 합니다. 따라서 여러분은
introducing coupling at runtime, which may not be apparent, but it's something you have to consider,
런타임에 커플링을 도입하는 것인데, 눈에 잘 띄지 않을 수도 있지만 반드시 고려해야 할 사항입니다,
and that is because if you ever wanted to extract individual modules into separate services,
개별 모듈을 별도의 서비스로 추출하고 싶을 때가 있기 때문입니다,
so now you're moving from a modular monolith into a microservice system, and you were using
따라서 이제 모듈형 모놀리스에서 마이크로서비스 시스템으로 이동하고 있고, 여러분은
method calls, your implementation would break because now your other module, for example,
메서드 호출을 사용했다면 이제 다른 모듈, 예를 들어
let's say the catalog module here, if it were a separate application, then those are different
여기서 카탈로그 모듈이 별도의 애플리케이션이라고 가정해 보겠습니다.
memories and you can't execute memory calls. So you would have to re-implement that public
메모리 호출을 실행할 수 없습니다. 따라서 해당 공개 모듈을 다시 구현해야 합니다.
interface, probably using HTTP calls over the network to be able to talk to other modules.
인터페이스를 다시 구현해야 하며, 아마도 다른 모듈과 통신하기 위해 네트워크를 통해 HTTP 호출을 사용해야 할 것입니다.
So now you switched runtime coupling for strong coupling over HTTP. So because of this,
이제 런타임 커플링을 HTTP를 통한 강력한 커플링으로 전환했습니다. 그래서 이 때문에
there's a different approach, which I'm very, I'm more a fan of than the previous one,
다른 접근 방식이 생겼는데, 저는 이 접근 방식이 이전 방식보다 더 마음에 듭니다,
and this is module communication using messaging. So the benefit of this approach is that it is
메시징을 이용한 모듈 통신입니다. 이 접근법의 장점은 다음과 같습니다.
asynchronous. If modules want to interact with each other, they send messages over a message bus.
비동기식입니다. 모듈이 서로 상호 작용하려면 메시지 버스를 통해 메시지를 보냅니다.
It is also possible to implement RPC-like calls over a message bus. So if you're familiar with
메시지 버스를 통해 RPC와 유사한 호출을 구현할 수도 있습니다. 따라서
a library that is called mass transit, it implements this request response communication
라는 라이브러리에서 이러한 요청 응답 통신을 구현합니다.
model, where let's say the order module wants to request something from the catalog module.
모델에서 주문 모듈이 카탈로그 모듈에 무언가를 요청한다고 가정해 보겠습니다.
It would send a message to the queue. The catalog module would receive this message,
이 모듈은 대기열에 메시지를 보냅니다. 카탈로그 모듈은 이 메시지를 수신합니다,
handle it, and then send the message back, which would go back to the order module. Now, of course,
처리한 다음 메시지를 다시 보내면 주문 모듈로 다시 전달됩니다. 물론 이제
this subtracts away some important implementation details, like which queues are being used,
이렇게 하면 어떤 대기열이 사용 중인지와 같은 중요한 구현 세부 정보가 사라집니다,
and also you need some sort of correlation ID between messages so that you know what message
또한 어떤 메시지가 어떤 메시지인지 알 수 있도록 메시지 간의 일종의 상관 관계 ID가 필요합니다.
you are waiting back. But if you don't want to deal with these complexities, the mass transit
를 기다리고 있는지 알 수 있습니다. 그러나 이러한 복잡성을 처리하고 싶지 않다면 대량 전송
library implements this very nicely. So how you interact between modules using messaging is you
라이브러리가 이를 매우 훌륭하게 구현합니다. 따라서 메시지를 사용하여 모듈 간에 상호 작용하는 방법은 여러분이
define contracts or interfaces for your messages, and you can share these contracts using maybe a
메시지에 대한 컨트랙트나 인터페이스를 정의하고, 아마도
NuGet package or a shared library where either all your contracts for a single module reside,
NuGet 패키지 또는 단일 모듈에 대한 모든 컨트랙트가 있는 공유 라이브러리를 사용할 수 있습니다,
or you can even share all of the contracts for the entire application and kind of manage them all in
또는 전체 애플리케이션에 대한 모든 컨트랙트를 공유하고 이를 모두
one place. So the benefit of communication like this is that it is decoupled. If you do a thought
한 곳에서 관리할 수 있습니다. 이와 같은 커뮤니케이션의 장점은 분리되어 있다는 것입니다. 생각을 하면
experiment, let's say we want to again pull out the catalog module into a separate service.
다시 카탈로그 모듈을 별도의 서비스로 분리한다고 가정해 보겠습니다.
If we were using a message bus and everything was going over the bus by sending messages,
메시지 버스를 사용하고 있고 모든 것이 메시지 전송을 통해 버스를 통해 이루어지고 있다고 가정해 봅시다,
everything would still function the same because we are not relying on in-memory call to implement
구현하기 위해 인메모리 호출에 의존하지 않기 때문에 모든 것이 여전히 동일하게 작동합니다.
communication. We are using an external system which still exists even if we were to go from a
통신을 구현하기 위해 인메모리 호출에 의존하지 않기 때문입니다. 우리는 여전히 존재하는 외부 시스템을 사용하고 있습니다.
modular monolith into microservices. So this is one very big advantage of this approach. Of course,
모듈형 모놀리스를 마이크로서비스로 전환하더라도 여전히 존재하는 외부 시스템을 사용하고 있습니다. 이것이 바로 이 접근 방식의 매우 큰 장점입니다. 물론이죠,
the downside is that you do get reduced performance if you rely on too much messaging.
단점은 너무 많은 메시징에 의존하면 성능이 저하될 수 있다는 것입니다.
So you're making a trade-off. If you expect that your modular monolith is realistically going to
그래서 절충안을 만들어야 합니다. 모듈형 모놀리스가 현실적으로 다음과 같은 성능을 낼 것으로 예상한다면
move into microservices, maybe you're better off using this approach from the start of your project.
마이크로서비스로 전환하는 것이 현실적으로 어렵다면 프로젝트 시작부터 이 접근 방식을 사용하는 것이 더 나을 수도 있습니다.
And again, the benefit is it's easy to extract modules into separate services.
다시 말하지만, 모듈을 별도의 서비스로 추출하기가 쉽다는 이점이 있습니다.
This is kind of the high level of how you communicate between your modules. You can either use
이것은 모듈 간에 통신하는 방법의 높은 수준입니다. 다음 중 하나를 사용할 수 있습니다.
memory in-memory metal calls or you can use messaging over a message bus. For example,
메모리 인메모리 메탈 호출을 사용하거나 메시지 버스를 통한 메시징을 사용할 수 있습니다. 예를 들어
we used a Revit MQ. Now another important thing that you need to consider apart from messaging is
에서는 Revit MQ를 사용했습니다. 이제 메시징과 별도로 고려해야 할 또 다른 중요한 사항이 있습니다.
the independence of data between modules. So every module is responsible for its own data.
모듈 간 데이터의 독립성입니다. 즉, 모든 모듈은 자체 데이터를 책임집니다.
So this is a constraint that you have to impose on the system because if you break this and you
따라서 이것은 시스템에 부과해야 하는 제약 조건입니다. 왜냐하면 이것을 위반하면
allow sharing of data between your modules, then you're going to end up with a mess.
모듈 간에 데이터 공유를 허용하면 결국 엉망이 될 것이기 때문입니다.
So another rule that you have to enforce in your application is that querying data directly
따라서 애플리케이션에 적용해야 하는 또 다른 규칙은 데이터를 직접 쿼리하는 것은
from different modules in the system is not allowed, which comes hand in hand with the fact
데이터를 직접 쿼리하는 것은 허용되지 않는다는 것입니다.
that every module needs to be responsible for its own data. And to achieve this, you have different
모든 모듈이 자신의 데이터를 책임져야 한다는 사실과 관련이 있습니다. 그리고 이를 달성하기 위해
levels of data isolation that you can resort to. And I'm going to talk about these data isolation
데이터 격리 수준을 선택할 수 있습니다. 이러한 데이터 격리에 대해 설명하겠습니다.
levels right now. But again, I want to stress and highlight this again. Every module in your system
수준에 대해 설명하겠습니다. 하지만 다시 한 번 강조하고 강조하고 싶습니다. 시스템의 모든 모듈
has to be responsible for its own data and there is no querying of data from other modules. So you
는 자체 데이터를 책임져야 하며 다른 모듈의 데이터를 쿼리할 수 없습니다. 따라서
can't directly access the database of other modules. So let's talk about how we can isolate
다른 모듈의 데이터베이스에 직접 액세스할 수 없습니다. 따라서 어떻게 분리할 수 있는지 이야기해 보겠습니다.
data between modules. So there are four levels and the first level is no isolation. So everything is
데이터를 격리하는 방법에 대해 알아보겠습니다. 네 가지 수준이 있으며 첫 번째 수준은 격리가 없습니다. 따라서 모든 것이
in one physical database and there is no isolation between modules. And this is
하나의 물리적 데이터베이스에 있으며 모듈 간에 격리되지 않습니다. 그리고 이것은
the worst approach possible and definitely the one that you should not even consider.
최악의 접근 방식이며 절대 고려하지 말아야 할 접근 방식입니다.
So here the problem is you are probably using foreign keys between tables in different modules,
여기서 문제는 아마도 다른 모듈의 테이블 간에 외래 키를 사용하고 있다는 것입니다,
which introduces coupling. So if you tried to extract these tables, you would run into a problem
를 사용하여 커플링이 발생한다는 것입니다. 따라서 이러한 테이블을 추출하려고 하면 다음과 같은 문제가 발생합니다.
because your foreign keys would now break and so on. So one level up in terms of isolation
외래 키가 깨지는 등의 문제가 발생합니다. 따라서 분리 측면에서 한 단계 업그레이드되었습니다.
is still using the same database, but using a different schema per module. So now you're,
는 여전히 동일한 데이터베이스를 사용하지만 모듈별로 다른 스키마를 사용합니다. 이제 여러분은
okay, you're still in the same database, but you're achieving at least logical separation
좋아, 여전히 같은 데이터베이스를 사용하고 있지만 최소한 논리적 분리는 이루어지고 있습니다.
of tables inside of the database. So in the example here, each of the modules from our example
의 테이블을 분리합니다. 따라서 여기 예제에서 예제의 각 모듈은
architecture has its own schema. And another thing that you want to impose here is to not use
아키텍처에는 고유한 스키마가 있습니다. 그리고 여기서 한 가지 더 강조하고 싶은 것은
foreign keys, even though you can, because this is going to make it easier for you to migrate into
외래 키를 사용할 수 있지만, 이렇게 하면 마이그레이션이 더 쉬워지므로
more constructive levels of data isolation. And again, each module can only query the tables from
보다 건설적인 수준의 데이터 격리가 가능합니다. 그리고 다시 말하지만, 각 모듈은 다음의 테이블만 쿼리할 수 있습니다.
its own schema. So no querying between schemas. That's very important to have a proper modular
까지만 쿼리할 수 있습니다. 따라서 스키마 간 쿼리는 불가능합니다. 이는 제대로 된 모듈형 데이터베이스에 매우 중요합니다.
modulif. Now the next level of isolation, if separate schemas are not enough, is using
모듈리프. 이제 분리된 스키마로 충분하지 않은 경우 다음 단계의 격리는
different physical databases. So let's say we're still using SQL, but each of our modules has its
다른 물리적 데이터베이스를 사용하는 것입니다. 따라서 여전히 SQL을 사용하고 있지만 각 모듈에 각각
own database. Now this can all be on the same database server, but at least it's a separate
자체 데이터베이스를 가지고 있습니다. 이제 이 모든 것이 동일한 데이터베이스 서버에 있을 수도 있지만, 적어도 별도의
physically isolated database. So you can't really easily query between the databases without
물리적으로 격리된 데이터베이스입니다. 따라서 데이터베이스 간에 쉽게 쿼리할 수 없습니다.
introducing a distributed transaction and you don't want to go there. So this is probably
분산 트랜잭션을 도입하지 않고는 쉽게 쿼리할 수 없습니다. 따라서 이것은 아마도
something that you may want to consider, either this approach or this approach, if you were to
이 접근 방식이나 이 접근 방식 중 하나를 고려할 수 있습니다.
start out. And then there is one more level, which is kind of exotic, but if you need this
시작하세요. 그리고 한 단계 더 있는데, 다소 이색적이지만 다음과 같은 방법이 필요합니다.
kind of isolation, it's very interesting. And that is, now you have different databases for each
고립된 상태라면 매우 흥미롭습니다. 즉, 이제 각각에 대해 서로 다른 데이터베이스를 갖게 됩니다.
module, but you're also using different database type or database management system. So let's say
모듈에 대해 서로 다른 데이터베이스 유형 또는 데이터베이스 관리 시스템을 사용하고 있다는 것입니다. 따라서 다음과 같이 가정해 보겠습니다.
for the order module, we want that relational guarantees and joins. So we opted for a SQL
주문 모듈의 경우 관계형 보증 및 조인이 필요합니다. 그래서 우리는 SQL
database. Now for the catalog module, where we are dealing with products and product information
데이터베이스를 선택했습니다. 이제 제품 및 제품 정보를 다루는 카탈로그 모듈을 살펴보겠습니다.
and a lot of unstructured data, we want to use maybe a document database. For the customers
그리고 많은 비정형 데이터는 문서 데이터베이스를 사용하려고 합니다. 고객을 위해
module, where we have a lot of relationships between customers, we opted for a graph database
모듈의 경우 고객 간의 관계가 많기 때문에 그래프 데이터베이스를 선택했습니다.
and for collaboration for some reason, just to make this slide look better probably,
그리고 어떤 이유에서인지 협업을 위해, 아마도 이 슬라이드를 더 보기 좋게 만들기 위해서였을 것입니다,
we used a column store database. So you can even do something like this, where you have both
열 저장소 데이터베이스를 사용했습니다. 따라서 다음과 같은 작업을 수행할 수도 있습니다.
physically separate databases between modules and also an entirely different database type,
모듈 간에 물리적으로 분리된 데이터베이스와 완전히 다른 데이터베이스 유형을 사용할 수도 있습니다,
which fits the needs of that module. So you have a lot of freedom when it comes to
모듈의 필요에 맞는 데이터베이스를 만들 수 있습니다. 따라서 다음과 같은 측면에서 많은 자유를 누릴 수 있습니다.
how much isolation you want to impose on your database. A good start again is probably using
데이터베이스에 얼마나 많은 격리를 적용할지 결정할 수 있습니다. 다시 시작하는 것이 좋습니다.
either the same database and a different schema per module or using different databases,
동일한 데이터베이스와 모듈마다 다른 스키마를 사용하거나 다른 데이터베이스를 사용하는 것입니다,
but still using the same database type. For example, all of your databases are PostgreSQL.
이지만 여전히 동일한 데이터베이스 유형을 사용합니다. 예를 들어 모든 데이터베이스가 PostgreSQL인 경우입니다.
And this more or less wraps up the story of how you can build a modular monolith.
이것으로 모듈형 모놀리스를 구축하는 방법에 대한 이야기가 어느 정도 마무리되었습니다.
And I want to share with you a few lessons, a few hardships that we encountered
그리고 몇 가지 교훈과 우리가 겪은 몇 가지 어려움을 여러분과 나누고 싶습니다.
in the previous two years while working on this architecture,
지난 2년간 이 아키텍처를 개발하면서 겪었던 어려움들을요,
so that you don't have to make the same mistakes that we did.
여러분은 우리와 같은 실수를 하지 않아도 됩니다.
So the first lesson or learning that I would like to share is you should spend more time
그래서 제가 나누고 싶은 첫 번째 교훈이나 배움은 더 많은 시간을 투자해야 한다는 것입니다.
defining module boundaries, and I promise it's going to pay dividends later.
모듈 경계를 정의하는 데 더 많은 시간을 투자해야 한다는 것입니다.
This is because when you're first starting out, it really isn't apparent how your system is going
처음 시작할 때는 시스템이 어떻게 돌아가는지 명확하지 않기 때문입니다.
to evolve. So if you spend a considerable amount of time at the beginning of the project,
진화할지 알 수 없기 때문입니다. 따라서 프로젝트 초기에 상당한 시간을 할애하면
just thinking how your system is going to grow, what are the parts of the system that kind of
시스템이 어떻게 성장할지, 시스템의 어떤 부분이 어떤 식으로
we may want to make independent in the future, you're going to end up with a lot better defined
우리가 미래에 독립하고 싶을지도 모른다고 생각하면, 훨씬 더 잘 정의되고
modules. And this is going to allow you to both develop your system faster and kind of later
모듈을 갖게 될 것입니다. 이렇게 하면 시스템을 더 빠르게 개발할 수 있을 뿐 아니라 나중에
scale it out in a much more performant way. So the next thing is about eventual consistency,
훨씬 더 고성능으로 확장할 수 있습니다. 다음은 최종적인 일관성에 관한 것입니다,
and eventual consistency is great. You can achieve it in a modular system, in a modular
그리고 최종적인 일관성은 훌륭합니다. 모듈형 시스템에서, 모듈형 시스템에서, 모듈형 시스템에서 이를 달성할 수 있습니다.
monolith system. You should definitely use it, but you need to plan for it. So one issue that we ran
모놀리스 시스템. 반드시 사용해야 하지만 이에 대한 계획이 필요합니다. 그래서 우리가 실행한 한 가지 이슈는
into was we designed all of our modules to be independent and they were communicating by using
모든 모듈을 독립적으로 설계하고, 모듈이 통신할 때
messages over the service bus. And we kind of implemented the entire system to be eventually
메시지를 사용하여 통신했습니다. 그리고 전체 시스템을 구현하여 결국에는
consistent. And we ran into an issue where kind of the eventual consistency came back to bite us.
일관성을 유지했습니다. 그런데 이 일관성이 결국 문제가 되어 돌아왔습니다.
So you have to consider how eventual consistency is going to reflect on your user experience
따라서 최종적인 일관성이 사용자 경험에 어떻게 반영될지 고려해야 합니다.
and maybe where you don't have the luxury of using eventual consistency,
최종 일관성을 사용할 여건이 되지 않을 수도 있습니다,
because some changes in your data may be slow to reflect on the user interface,
데이터의 일부 변경 사항이 사용자 인터페이스에 반영되는 속도가 느릴 수 있기 때문입니다,
and this is going to lead to bad user experience. Now there are ways to go around this.
이는 사용자 경험 저하로 이어질 수 있습니다. 이제 이 문제를 해결할 수 있는 방법이 있습니다.
For example, your user interface can do eager updates, kind of behave like the update is already
예를 들어, 사용자 인터페이스에서 업데이트가 이미 완료된 것처럼 동작하도록 할 수 있습니다.
applied in the database and wait for the server to respond to kind of confirm, yes, this went through
데이터베이스에 적용하고 서버가 일종의 확인을 위해 응답할 때까지 기다립니다.
or no, it didn't. Another thing is you can have maybe some sort of WebSockets connection
또는 아니요, 그렇지 않습니다. 또 다른 한 가지는 아마도 웹 소켓 연결의 일종인
between your backend and your front end, where as soon as the system converges
백엔드와 프론트엔드 사이에서 시스템이 수렴하자마자
into an eventually consistent state, you notify your application, your front end application,
결국 일관된 상태가 되면 프론트엔드 애플리케이션인 애플리케이션에 알립니다,
or other times you're going to have to resort to some way to manage consistency so that it's not
또는 다른 경우에는 일관성을 관리하기 위해 어떤 방법을 사용해야 합니다.
eventual, either using distributed transactions, which is something you don't want to do because
결국에는 분산 트랜잭션을 사용하거나, 분산 트랜잭션을 사용하지 않는 것이 좋습니다.
it's very complicated and slow. Also maybe something like a two-phase commit, which is again
매우 복잡하고 느리기 때문입니다. 또한 2단계 커밋과 같은 것일 수도 있습니다.
leaning into distributed transactions, or you may come to the natural conclusion that,
분산 트랜잭션에 기대거나, 아니면 자연스럽게 결론에 도달할 수도 있습니다,
okay, we need consistency here. We can't rely on eventual consistency. So maybe these modules
여기에는 일관성이 필요합니다. 우리는 최종적인 일관성에 의존할 수 없습니다. 따라서 이 모듈은
should be merged together. And this is also something that we kind of learned along the way,
을 병합해야 합니다. 이 또한 우리가 그 과정에서 배운 점입니다,
and it comes kind of as a conclusion of my first point here, that you should spend more time
그리고 이것은 제 첫 번째 요점의 결론으로, 여러분이 더 많은 시간을 할애해야 한다는 것입니다.
defining your modules. What we did was we made possibly too many modules and some of them ended
모듈을 정의하는 데 더 많은 시간을 할애해야 한다는 것입니다. 우리가 한 일은 아마도 너무 많은 모듈을 만들었고 그 중 일부는 끝났습니다.
up being chatty. What I mean by this is you're going to see that some parts in your system,
수다스러워졌습니다. 무슨 말이냐면, 시스템에서 어떤 부분이 작동을 멈추는 것을 보게 될 것입니다,
from different modules, are going to be communicating with each other very frequently.
서로 다른 모듈의 일부가 매우 자주 통신하게 될 것입니다.
We can say that they are chatty. So this should lead you to either two conclusions.
수다스럽다고 말할 수 있습니다. 따라서 두 가지 결론을 내릴 수 있습니다.
One is that your module boundaries are messed up. So you put some things of your system into
하나는 모듈 경계가 엉망이라는 것입니다. 그래서 시스템의 일부를
separated modules and they shouldn't be, they should be together. Or your modules are too
분리된 모듈에 넣어서는 안 되고 함께 있어야 합니다. 또는 모듈이 너무
granular. So you should merge them maybe into one big module and this is going to solve the
세분화되어 있을 수도 있습니다. 따라서 모듈을 하나의 큰 모듈로 병합해야 하며 이렇게 하면
chattiness. And one last point I want to highlight is that you need to carefully plan how you're
수다스러움을 해결할 수 있습니다. 마지막으로 한 가지 강조하고 싶은 점은 어떻게 하면
going to share data between your modules. So, and this goes hand in hand with chattiness because
모듈 간에 데이터를 어떻게 공유할 것인지 신중하게 계획해야 한다는 것입니다. 이는 수다스러움과도 밀접한 관련이 있습니다.
chattiness is, occurs because you're probably missing data from one module in the other,
수다스러움은 한 모듈의 데이터가 다른 모듈에 누락되어 있기 때문에 발생합니다,
so they have to constantly talk to each other. So how do you share data between modules?
따라서 서로 끊임없이 대화해야 합니다. 그렇다면 모듈 간에 데이터를 어떻게 공유할 수 있을까요?
Probably the most decoupled solution to this, and the one I think you should consider, is
아마도 이 문제에 대한 가장 분리된 솔루션이자 여러분이 고려해야 할 솔루션은 다음과 같습니다.
you want your modules to be publishing messages whenever some important change occurs. And then
중요한 변경 사항이 발생할 때마다 모듈이 메시지를 게시하도록 하는 것입니다. 그리고
the other modules can subscribe to that and possibly store that data into a local copy.
에 메시지를 게시하면 다른 모듈이 이를 구독하고 해당 데이터를 로컬 복사본에 저장할 수 있습니다.
So that when they need this data, they no need to go to the other module to get it at runtime.
따라서 이 데이터가 필요할 때 다른 모듈로 이동하여 런타임에 데이터를 가져올 필요가 없습니다.
So that's one approach. The other approach would be maybe using some sort of caching mechanism.
이것이 한 가지 접근 방식입니다. 다른 접근 방식은 일종의 캐싱 메커니즘을 사용하는 것입니다.
So, okay, if I have to go to the other module to get some piece of information, I'll pay the cost
좋아요, 어떤 정보를 얻기 위해 다른 모듈로 이동해야 한다면 그 비용을 지불할게요.
of a network round trip once, and I'm going to cache that data locally so that I can reuse it
의 네트워크 왕복 비용을 지불하고, 그 데이터를 재사용할 수 있도록 로컬에 캐시할 것입니다.
for some given period of time while that cache is valid. So this kind of wraps up the main pain
캐시가 유효한 동안 일정 기간 동안 재사용할 수 있습니다. 이렇게 하면 큰 문제가 해결됩니다.
points that we had in building a modular monolith, and I hope that this was informative.
모듈형 모놀리스를 구축할 때 겪었던 어려움에 대해 설명해 드렸는데, 도움이 되셨기를 바랍니다.
So with this, I'm going to move into the Q&A section.
이것으로 Q&A 섹션으로 넘어가겠습니다.